hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of Holo talk
for the week of April 2nd 2000. we
continue our series of recordings that
we made at the center for the
holographic arts in Long Island City New
York and Michelle Roy once again joins
me in the studio hello Frank I'm already
interrupting you
this week Our Guest is Mary Harmon and
Michelle you did the interview with Mary
and basically you were there to find out
information on why artists would you to
work in the field of holography and I
think you were sort of like approaching
it as a career but as we found out as
the evening progressed it's just not a
career choice I guess for artists to get
involved compared to someone who would
want to get involved with commercial
holography right I think that um artists
probably what I got out of talking to
Mary was that artists more so than a lot
of other people when they think about
you know their careers is that art is a
passion for them and it's something that
they really can't even control because
she talks about how you know even as a
child she was you know sketching and
drawing and painting and so forth in
fact she her career was uh that she was
a nurse and then right and then art was
just something that you know consumed
her more and more and so now that's
become you know her life I don't think
it's just unique to holography though I
imagine with photography commercial
photographers just like you have
commercial holographers and I would
imagine anyone who would want to
approach photography or any of the other
Arts would find
it's a very hard career path oh yeah
well and I think a lot of it has to do
with you know
you know money I mean you have to be
able to support yourself somehow so
um she talked about that that was not
something that you know she needed to
have a way to pay the bills and that's
what you know being a nurse was about
but you know the art is sort of what
feeds her soul you know on the flip side
of that on the money issue it's a very
expensive field traditionally to get
involved with but fortunately with the
Advent of the semiconductor diode lasers
I would think that we will start to see
more people have the ability to get
involved with holography and artists
having more of an ability to manipulate
the technology themselves because I
think you know Mary talked about how at
the beginning she was having other
people you know do the the shots for her
but then she slowly is starting to get
more involved but I think with the the
laser diode technology that you're not
as intimidated by you know there isn't
this enormous you know laser and it's
not as expensive to an investment that
you have to make in order to to start
experimenting and playing random
learning the skills and the techniques
so the work that she had there I think
was dedicated to her mother who had
recently passed away and that
interesting because just about two weeks
before that you produce a hologram here
in the lab right that was a piece from
your mother which is based basically
just about saying right yes right my
mother died when I was two and a half
and my grandparents had sent me a few
years ago a number of things that have
belonged to her so then when we talked
about me making a hologram and what
would I make a whole gram of I went
looking through her things to see if I
could find something because I wanted to
you know sort of be able to have a
another kind of recording of you know
her and and it's a piece of her so which
is very similar to what Mary did yeah we
had spoken a little bit about combining
that whole gram with other elements as
well which was right up which is right
yeah which is what Mary did yeah so we
weren't copying Mary
speaking of which that peace that you
did will be on display down at the
Smithsonian and we're going we're going
on there two dates
public that's actually National Teachers
Conference
that will be open to the public will be
May 6th and we would like to invite
Hollow talk listeners who are in the I
guess the Northeast Corridor willing to
come down to the Smithsonian and we're
going to have a number of different
holograms on exhibit especially the
diode Holograms because basically this
is going to be at the hershon Museum
which is an art institute there as part
of the Smithsonian and one of the things
that we want to push is the fact that
because you know holography was such an
expensive medium to get involved with
for so many years a lot of artists just
didn't want to make the investment in
doing that but never couldn't make the
Improvement exactly but now it's well
within the realm of I'd say mood I mean
that's a relative thing you know whether
someone can afford something or not yeah
but it's 60 bucks Frank to you know get
your whole set up together so you know I
think sure and then to move up to the
more powerful right exactly so you're
still only looking at around 250 270
compared to thousands of dollars right
previously so hopefully we'll be able to
allow people to have that realization
that holography is now not something
that's Out Of Reach anymore
let's start seeing people get involved
right and be able to experiment more
with it as well yeah exactly because
they you don't have to go through all
that Hassle and expense yeah so uh
yeah I was just going to invite people
to come down yeah please join us and we
will be doing presentations throughout
the day and we're going to put a web
page up I think it may be finished this
weekend where you can get more
information look on the whole talk page
for uh information on our Smithsonian
presentations click on that link and
then it will take you right to the page
to get more information and if your
holotech listener who comes down let us
know we'll come up we would love to you
know know that you're someone who
listens to the show and be able to get a
chance to chat with you all three of you
well that way we won't be overwhelmed
anything else you want to add before we
move on no sorry I didn't mean to cut in
like that
that's it I'm done okay thanks for
tuning in to Hall talk see you next week
bye
okay we're back with the show and we're
sitting here or I'm standing Michelle
it's sitting and we're here with Mary
Harmon who has a number of uh beautiful
white light reflection Holograms in the
show image plane to work uh could you
tell us a little bit about the work did
you have a certain theme that you were
working with or anything that's special
about the work itself right I um I
brought the work uh the ideas I brought
into the to the hollow center originally
I wanted to do still life because I'm a
painter and I was painting um uh I paint
very realistically and was doing some um
what I call the vanity class series
based on the Dutch still like paintings
so that was one idea I thought well I
want to do some still lives and I set up
a few things for that but the other idea
I had was a lot more personal and it had
to do uh with uh uh I wanted to recreate
a time in my life and that was my first
Community went in 1950 and this all came
about over the last few years I've been
working on this my mother was sick and
died of cancer probably about the same
time I think she died just when I put
the proposal in and then I took some of
the objects from her from her house and
made Holograms of it I really just want
to document some of these objects and it
turned into something a little more I
think over the year I've been working on
it and finally finished most of the
installation this uh just about a month
ago and it's it's I think it's still
growing a little bit I don't know if
you've you've caught that I didn't write
a lot about where this stuff all came
from I didn't want want that yet
and that's about it so I got two Series
going in this and the still lives and
and what I call the first communion
project which I think yet is going to
get bigger I've done some paintings with
it as well which we didn't have
after
that I can see doing a whole room of the
Holograms uh some more boxes and maybe
some of the real objects as well and the
paintings
so yeah did you produce all the works
here at the center oh absolutely
absolutely so what
um The Artisan residency they accepted
my proposal and then we did all we made
all the Masters here during The
Residency and then
I we did that over three days and then I
came back later and did the transfers so
so uh Dan and Anna Maria did all the
technical work as well which I mean you
could see the quality and that's dance
dance influence there and I mean they're
really they're bright they're the really
the brightest Holograms I think I've
ever ever produced they're very bright
and clean did you do any of the
processing dark room work
um no I'm just curious what processing
technique you used for them because
they're so Crystal Clear and they are
very bright and they're on active
materials so we're starting to get used
to seeing brighter results on the
slavage and HRT materials but
I'd say that the shots that you have out
there can compare to anything that's
been done on those materials on the
accent
um part we weren't quite sure just
things were just working right uh we we
seem to get the exposures right and the
the Masters were so bright and I always
thought it was the choice of objects I
used you notice I used a lot of glass
mirror that's the first time I played
with Mir I didn't know what was going to
happen
whether the whether the pulse the light
was gonna
bout and ruin our image completely and
it didn't it just everything just got
sharp those little figures uh there's
one figure in there that's made out of
uh clay and it's sort of a pinkish color
and that seemed to I don't know it held
the light or something I don't know and
and all the reflections the reflective
material it um it worked a lot better
than than we thought was that who knows
that old word again there was a magic
here when we uh we were shooting and it
was like we couldn't do anything wrong
you mentioned a pulse or are they pulse
work oh they're awkward oh yeah yeah we
didn't set anything up continuous way no
no
to do the Masters why did you choose to
do that with the inanimate objects just
out of curiosity use a pulse laser
um
I don't know I'm just you know well it's
a question no it's it's quick you know I
mean you're when you set up inanimate
objects you know we're talking a couple
days setting up and hot gluing I mean
man we just set these right up in front
and chopped and there's there's our
first Master you know we were doing a
couple Masters three Masters a day I
came up with 10 masters in in three days
now do you have a studio of your own as
well no no
I uh I got into when well I've always I
I first in 1985 my first experience was
holography I was in Toronto and um uh
Michael saudin did some of my images so
I always paid the technicians to do my
work that was with the Fringe research
that's right French research yeah way
back then and uh then I worked with
Michael page Ontario College of Art but
basically all the time I uh paid people
to do my work for me Melissa Crenshaw in
Vancouver I ran at Doris Villa's Lab One
Summer so by the time I you know after a
few years of getting other people to do
my work I wanted to learn to do
holography so I took some courses did
dance course and uh then did an artisan
residency at the Museum here it was my
first time doing holograms on my own it
was great I mean I just and then I ran
at Doris's Lab One Summer and just did
nothing but
Dawn Till Dawn shot my own work for the
first darsh works a lot with white light
transmission work did you do reflection
work there or did you work with
transmission totally reflection I've
never done white light transmission
um uh
for whatever reason I don't know maybe
just the limit I wanted to really limit
what I what I was doing because I didn't
know anything you know so I'll just hone
in on one thing plus I like I I've
always I like doing objects the real
objects and uh and um I want I like that
physicality that they give me even
though you're you're depth you know so
so what you got 10 inches of depth of
depth to play with so I like those
limitations too well what can I come up
with that you know so uh start using a
diet laser you'll get more depth than
that oh yeah
I'm gonna turn the microphone over
Michelle and Michelle's you have a few
other questions here
turn it over to me
yeah
we'll we'll see you you know I'm I'm
open I I it was so exciting this is the
most I didn't do work since 90 I think
91 or 92 I worked in Doris's lab and I
haven't done holography since and when I
put in this proposal I I was I've been
painting I said I'm not going to do a
large anymore I don't have any money to
do holography you know that's what I
never worked on film what am I going to
do you know they they don't make us
glass plates anymore so this was just
wonderful to be working in it again
that old
wow creativity you know this is the most
creative medium you can work in you know
it's it's like everything's wide open so
do you now you you're a painter
um which would you I mean is there are
there certain things that you can
express through your painting that you
can't through holography and certain
things that you can express through
holography that you can't through your
painting I mean how does that go
together
yeah yeah no they're not they're not
compatible I've tried
um you know the best I could do I
painted the tape on those boxes you know
a little Trump Leo on that but other
than that I've tried to put a painting
next to a hologram and uh it's two
different mediums find that you're doing
different kinds of work in holography as
opposed to what you do in your painting
um I mean I know you talked about the
realism in your painting but you know do
you find that you're you're trying to
express different things do you know
what I'm saying
um well it's it's just it's okay one
holography is sculptural holography is
three-dimensional
painting is two-dimensional I mean start
with that I mean and with the with uh
when I'm trying to paint realistically
I'm trying to make a two-dimensional
surface appear to be a three-dimensional
service so when I got a hologram I got a
three I got three dimensionalities so so
so my my my aim is different right away
right so uh so what do I do with the
Hologram then I have to play around with
with its own characteristics which is
transparent you know transparent
fleeting image you know and to me it's
always three-dimensional so
yeah it's just totally different medium
yeah but what what I'm saying I think I
talk about the same things I think I
think I I do
um I talk about you know death life yeah
pretty well that but uh in pain I mean I
can paint anything I can you know I can
do a landscape in in painting I can do a
huge painting of a very realistic
landscape I'm not about to attempt that
analogy
how are the what what made you decide
what attracted you to wanting to do
holography I mean obviously you were
attracted to the medium itself and
having other people do it but what made
you decide I want to do this you know
what what got you you know hooked on it
if you will I was I've always worked
with illusion I mean to me that's what
painting is right it's it's dealing with
like I said making a two something
appear something different and I was
um trying to at one point I was trying
to suspend some objects in air and
somebody said hey Jefferson hologram
this is you know again 85 show in
Toronto and I was just blown away here
were these little objects that were
floating there and it was so it was a
sculptural element of it that uh I could
I could if I could make an object that
floated in air you know right and that
was that was about it you know and and
pretty well nothing else at the time had
nothing to do with painting or whatever
okay
what what do you enjoy about working in
holography what is it that appeals to
you
um that makes you come back for more
obviously it's not the money because you
said there's no money in it but what is
it that appeals to you about it both
both in terms of you know how it lets
you express yourself but also
um just in uh you know physically
working with the medium because it's
very different I would assume I'm not an
artist myself but I would assume that
it's very different to paint than it is
to you know work in holography just you
know even physically you know I part of
it is that I never know what's what it's
what the final outcome is going to be
you know you can plan it and uh and and
it okay put that with the process you
know when I I bring in a model I set it
up on the table and and you see
something you know that you never
anticipated something happens and then I
can start changing something so it's a
creative process basically and uh
um
that's that's the exciting part I mean
even when I I Come Away with no I came
away with images so I had a doll I had a
lamp I had these holographic images so
what can
them I mean so it doesn't end when I
make an image then I take them all home
and I think okay now what can I do with
these things I start putting I keep the
images transparent I start putting
things behind and uh it's you know the
process continues it's it's just this
wonderful long creative process I can do
a lot of other things with these things
now you know I don't necessarily I'm not
stuck with that just that thing and
now if if someone were thinking about
wanting to you know get into
um not just even not just holography but
you know being an artist in general
um you know how what what kinds of words
of encouragement would you give them or
what what kinds of things would you tell
them to to be thinking about
um in terms of considering you know art
as a career
like to make a lot of money
out of money well you know I mean
I I think it's I I don't see it as
something anybody would ever say I'm
going to be an artist you know I think
that's something that comes with with
experience of Life whatever I mean it's
I would encourage a younger person well
I like Drew my father was a painter my
you know we all well we're good with our
hands
yeah but I did other things I I trained
as a nurse I worked for years as an RN
really oh yeah I worked in ICU up until
um 90 91 you know I mean
are you you're not I worked to support
my arms right you know it's as simple as
that you know but at the same time I was
involved in life you know I mean I
wasn't just making art I mean I was I
was involved in doing something else I
can't just I can't just paint or just
you know that's I mean you know I mean
read read history read you know read
poetry Read Literature do something at
you know do created
art comes from right yeah
no I I've uh I've always I've always you
know had some kind of job or something
in in that maybe grounded me I don't
know what the word you want to say I
mean I had kids I had uh you know I've
always done other things right now I've
you know got a little cabin up in
the back that I'm
wanting to get back and do the finish of
shingling I started last summer you know
I mean that's I love working I love
working with tools I took a carpentry
Course once when I got tired
and I was just going to do renovations
I mean that's I have to get away from
the art you know it's like I I'll go out
there and Hammer and work on something
work on a project I'll do the plumbing I
I you know I like doing like doing all
that stuff
and then the art will come you know I
don't sit there and try and think of
ideas
you know a lot of the earlier Holograms
out there I think were just
to to get
the release of some of the stress I had
working ICU I mean I did a lot of stuff
about death little ghosts and little
ghosts floating through things they were
all dealing with my experiences working
as a nurse
you think that was
you had those experiences that they sort
of gave you oh yeah I mean yeah I mean
I could never see myself as just doing
art I mean I I never really went to art
school and when I did I went to a couple
years to a place in Toronto called Art's
Sake when I was already in my late 30s
I just wanted to go to learn to paint
you know but I never really learned to
paint what I learned was there were a
lot of other people in the world who
felt like I did that had a passion for
uh
for for this stuff you know I've never
been I've never been in an art gallery
until I was a senior in high school I
went on a class trip to Washington DC
and I saw
um
probably the
the crucifixion
hanging in Washington DC so surrealism
right you know I mean that was I'm a
great all these guys you know I mean I
Christmas online
I mean my father's influenced too you
know
he was a Flemish oh okay my dad was a
Flemish painter
he was he was born in Kent and he
painted really yeah so there's genetic
there too you know we were eight of us
we're all good with our hands
well it's been very interesting I've
learned a lot I really appreciate it I
don't know if you have any more
questions for Mary Frank
any additional shows coming up anywhere
this is going to uh travel to another
location after it's finished here right
uh we're bringing the show in two weeks
to uh Fort Myers Florida
can't remember the name of the gallery
zaizai something anyway and then it's
going to Tucson the Contemporary Museum
of Art
for six weeks that's uh starting May
12th uh yeah May 12th it'll be in Tucson
for six weeks
and I'm very excited about that because
I got a big space and I think the
curator at Tucson Museum was a former
student of Dance
oh nice holographic connection there he
knows what the medium's about which is
it's nice to see this work starting to
go to contemporary museums I'm hoping to
get something going in Montreal at the
um
these are contemporary too I'm hoping
that that'll I'd like to do a big
installation combining holography and
painting in that
just getting the stuff into the
contemporary art galleries forget the
group forget the group science science
Tech shows and start getting holography
scene in the right venue it really is
important what do you think the biggest
drawback is for people to get
pornography is it the initial cost that
they have to put out for an investment
to start that's certainly that's what
you know yeah exactly
um
foreign
it's getting more so boy the classic
brushes try and get some good brushes
anymore but uh you know I mean there's
opportunities for anybody to take
weekend courses that's how I did it I
took a you know I wanted to learn about
holography I took a weekend course at
Fringe research
you know it was enough to get me going
and then I applied for an artisan
residency there and I got it you know I
didn't have any uh I didn't have any I
didn't need money to start
I just needed some good ideas and
learned how to write up a good proposal
hone your ideas do photographs first you
know do a professional job with this
stuff when you put a proposal in do it
wow that's the whole care
that's that okay there's a nice thread
between my nursing between my art
between the way I paint you know take
care do you know do it professionally
take care with what you do love it and
just love what you do the pieces yeah
it's a great way to stop well thank you
Mary you're welcome thank you